When I was 10 years old,
عندما كنت في العاشرة من عمري،
a cousin of mine took me on a tour of his medical school.
أخذني إبن عمي في زيارة لكلية الطب التي يدرس بها.
And as a special treat,
وكمعاملة خاصة لي
he took me to the pathology lab
أخذني إلى مختبر علم الأمراض/ الباثولوجي
and took a real human brain
وأخذ دماغًا بشريًأ حقيقيًا
out of the jar
إلى خارج الجرة
and placed it in my hands.
ووضعه على يديا
And there it was,
وكان هناك،
the seat of human consciousness,
مقر الوعي البشري،
the powerhouse of the human body,
مركز نفوذ الجسم البشري،
sitting in my hands.
يجلس على راحة يديا
And that day I knew that when I grew up,
وفي ذلك اليوم عرفت انني عندما أكبر،
I was going to become a brain doctor,
سأصبح طبيبة مخ،
scientist, something or the other.
عالمة، شيء أو آخر.
Years later, when I finally grew up,
بعد أعوام لاحقة، عندما كبرت
my dream came true.
أصبح حلمي حقيقة
And it was while I was doing my Ph.D.
وكان خلال فترة دراستي لنيل الدكتوراة
on the neurological causes
في الدوافع العصبية
of dyslexia in children
لعسر القراءة لدى الأطفال
that I encountered a startling fact
واجهتني حقيقة مروعة
that I'd like to share with you all today.
اود مشاركتها معكم جميعًا اليوم
It is estimated that one in six children,
تشير التقديرات أن واحدا من بين ستة اطفال،
that's one in six children,
إنه واحد من بين ستة أطفال
suffer from some developmental disorder.
يعاني من بعض إضطرابات النمو.
This is a disorder that
إنه الاضطراب الذي
retards mental development in the child
يعيق نمو الذهن لدى الطفل
and causes permanent mental impairments.
ويسبب عاهات ذهنية دائمة
Which means that each and every one of you here today
والذي يعني أن كل واحد منكم هنا اليوم
knows at least one child that is suffering
يعرف على الأقل طفلا واحدا يعاني
from a developmental disorder.
من اضطراب النمو
But here's what really perplexed me.
لكن هنا ما يحيرني حقا.
Despite the fact that each
بالرغم من حقيقة ان كل
and every one of these disorders
واحدة من هذه الإضطرابات
originates in the brain,
تنشأ في الدماغ،
most of these disorders
غالبية هذه الاضطرابات
are diagnosed solely on the basis
يتم تشخيصها فقط على أساس
of observable behavior.
مراقبة السلوك
But diagnosing a brain disorder
لكن تشخيص اضطراب الدماغ
without actually looking at the brain
دون النظر بصورة فعلية في الدماغ
is analogous to treating a patient with a heart problem
يشابه علاج مريض يعاني من مشاكل في القلب
based on their physical symptoms,
اعتمادا على الأعرض الجسدية،
without even doing an ECG or a chest X-ray
حتى دون عمل تخطيط القلب أو أشعة أكس للصدر
to look at the heart.
للنظر في القلب.
It seemed so intuitive to me.
إنه يبدو من البديعي بالنسبة لي.
To diagnose and treat a brain disorder accurately,
لتشخيص ومعالجة اضطرابات الدماغ بدقة،
it would be necessary to look at the brain directly.
من الضروري أن ننظر إلى الدماغ مباشرةً
Looking at behavior alone
النظر إلى السلوك منفردًا
can miss a vital piece of the puzzle
يمكن أن يفقد جزءا مهما في حل اللغز
and provide an incomplete, or even a misleading,
,تقديم صورة غير كاملة، أو حتى خادعة،
picture of the child's problems.
عن مشاكل الطفل
Yet, despite all the advances in medical technology,
مع ذلك, وبرغم كل التطورات في التقنية الطبية،
the diagnosis of brain disorders
تشخيص اضطرابات الدماغ
in one in six children
لكل طفل من بين ستة اطفال
still remained so limited.
- مازال محدودًا جدا.
And then I came across a team at Harvard University
وثم إلتقيت بفريق من جامعة هارفرد
that had taken one such advanced medical technology
والذي إتخذ تقنية طبية متطورة
and finally applied it,
وأخيرًا تم تطبيقها،
instead of in brain research,
بدلا عن أبحاث الدماغ،
towards diagnosing brain disorders in children.
نحو تشخيص اضطرابات الدماغ لدى الأطفال
Their groundbreaking technology
تقنيتهم الرائدة
records the EEG, or the electrical activity
تسجل تخطيط المخ أو الأنشطة الكهربائية
of the brain, in real time,
للدماغ في الوقت الحقيقي،
allowing us to watch the brain
لتسمح لنا بمشاهدة الدماغ
as it performs various functions
عندما يقوم بأداء وظائفه المختلفة
and then detect even the slightest abnormality
ثم تكشف أدنى شذوذ
in any of these functions:
في أي من هذه الوظائف
vision, attention, language, audition.
البصر, التركيز, اللغة, السمع.
A program called Brain Electrical
برنامج يسمى تخطيط
Activity Mapping
أنشطة المخ الكهربائي
then triangulates the source
ثم يحدد مصدر
of that abnormality in the brain.
ذلك الشذوذ في الدماغ.
And another program called
وبرنامج اخر يسمى
Statistical Probability Mapping
تخطيط الإحتمالات الإحصائية
then performs mathematical calculations
بعدها يقوم بإجراء الحسابات الرياضية
to determine whether any of these abnormalities
لتحديد إذا ما كان إحدى هذه الشذوذ
are clinically significant,
هي ذات أهمية طبيا
allowing us to provide a much more accurate
ليسمح لنا بلحصول على المزيد من دقة
neurological diagnosis
التشخيص العصبي
of the child's symptoms.
لأعراض الطفل.
And so I became the head of neurophysiology
وبالتالي أصبحت رئيسة فسم وظائف الأعضاء العصبية/الفيسولوجيا العصبية
for the clinical arm of this team,
للعيادة المصاحبة لهذا الفريق
and we're finally able to use this technology
وأخيرًا تمكنا من استخدام هذه التقنية
towards actually helping
بتقديم مساعدة فعلية
children with brain disorders.
للأطفال المصابين باضطرابات الدماغ
And I'm happy to say that I'm now in the process
ويسعدني أن اخبركم أنني بصدد
of setting up this technology here in India.
انشاء هذه التقنية هنا في الهند
I'd like to tell you about one such child,
أود أن أخبركم عن أحد هؤلاء الأطفال،
whose story was also covered by ABC News.
والذي قامت بعرض قصته قناة أيه بي سي نيوز.
Seven-year-old Justin Senigar
جستين سينغار البالغ من العمر سبعة اعوام
came to our clinic with this diagnosis
أتى إلى عيادتنا بتشخيص
of very severe autism.
لمرض التوحد الحاد
Like many autistic children,
كالعديد من الأطفال المصابين
his mind was locked inside his body.
كان دماغه محبوسًا داخل جسده
There were moments when he would
كانت هنالك لحظات عندما
actually space out for seconds at a time.
يفقد التركيز لعدة ثواني من الوقت.
And the doctors told his parents
وأخبر الأطباء والديه
he was never going to be able
بأنه لن يستطيع أبدًا
to communicate or interact socially,
التواصل أو التفاعل اجتماعيًا
and he would probably never have too much language.
ومن المحتمل أيضًا أن تكون لغته ضحلة.
When we used this groundbreaking EEG technology
عندما قمنا بإستخدام هذه التقنية الرائدة في مجال تخطيط الدماغ
to actually look at Justin's brain,
للنظر بدقة إلى دماغ جستين،
the results were startling.
كانت النتيجة مذهلة.
It turned out that Justin was almost
وجدنا أنه وبكل تأكيد
certainly not autistic.
لم يكن يعاني من مرض التوحد.
He was suffering from brain seizures
كان يعاني من مرض الصرع
that were impossible to see with the naked eye,
والذي من المستحيل اكتشافه بالعين المجردة،
but that were actually causing symptoms
لكن ذلك في الواقغ كان سبب تلك الأعراض
that mimicked those of autism.
التي تماثل أعراض مرض التوحد.
After Justin was given anti-seizure medication,
وبعد اعطاء جستين دواء مصاد للصرع،
the change in him was amazing.
حدث له تغير مذهل.
Within a period of 60 days,
خلال فترة 60 يومًا،
his vocabulary went from two to three words
تطورت محصلته اللغوية من اثنين إلى ثلاث كلمات
to 300 words.
لتصل إلى 300 كلمة.
And his communication and social interaction
وتواصله وتفاعله الإجتماعي
were improved so dramatically
تطور بشكل كبير جدا،
that he was enrolled into a regular school
فألتحق بمدرسة نظامية
and even became a karate super champ.
حتى أنه أصبح بطلا في لعبة الكاراتيه.
Research shows that 50 percent of children,
أظهرت نتيجة بحث أن نسبة 50% من الأطفال،
almost 50 percent of children
حوالي نسبة 50% من الأطفال
diagnosed with autism
الذين تم تشخيصهم بمرض التوحد
are actually suffering from hidden brain seizures.
يعانون فعلا من حالات كامنة للصرع.
These are the faces of the children
هذه هي أوجه الأطفال
that I have tested
الذين قمت باجراء اختبارات عليهم
with stories just like Justin.
وقصصهم شبيه بقصة جستين.
All these children
كل هؤلاء الأطفال
came to our clinic with a diagnosis
أتوا إلى عيادتنا بتشخيص
of autism, attention deficit disorder,
مرض التوحد، اضطرابات عجز الانتباه والتركيز،
mental retardation, language problems.
تخلف عقلي، مشاكل لغوية.
Instead, our EEG scans revealed
بدلاً من ذلك، فقد كشفت أشعتنا لتخطيط الدماغ
very specific problems hidden within their brains
عن مشاكل محددة كامنة في أدمغتهم
that couldn't possibly have been detected
والتي ربما لايمكن اكشافها
by their behavioral assessments.
عن طريق تقييم تصرفاتهم وسلوكياتهم.
So these EEG scans
وبالتالي هذه مجموعة أشعة تخطيط الدماغ
enabled us to provide these children
مكنتنا من تزويد هولاء الأطفال
with a much more accurate neurological diagnosis
بتشخيص عصبي أكثر دقة
and much more targeted treatment.
وعلاجًا أكثر استهدافًا للعلة.
For too long now, children with developmental disorders
لفترة طويلة الآن، الأطفال المصابون من اضطرابات النمو
have suffered from misdiagnosis
يعانون من خطأ في التشخيص
while their real problems have gone undetected
ولم يتم اكتشاف مشاكلهم الحقيقة.
and left to worsen.
وتركت لتتفاقم.
And for too long, these children and their parents
ولمدة طويلة, هؤلاء الأطفال وذويهم
have suffered undue frustration and desperation.
عانوا من الإحباط المفرط واليأس.
But we are now in a new era of neuroscience,
لكننا الآن نشهد عصرًا جديدًا في علم الأعصاب،
one in which we can finally look
والذي مكننا أخيرًا
directly at brain function in real time
من النظر مباشرةً إلى وظائف الدماغ في الوقت الحقيقي
with no risks and no side effects, non-invasively,
دون مخاطر وآثار جانبية، دون جراحة،
and find the true source
والحصول على المصدر الحقيقي
of so many disabilities in children.
للعديد من الإعاقات لدى الأطفال.
So if I could inspire
وهكذا لو أمكنني إلهام
even a fraction of you in the audience today
ولو جزء بسيط منكم في حضور اليوم
to share this pioneering diagnostic approach
لمشاركة هذا المنهج الرائد في التشخيص
with even one parent whose child
على الأقل مع أحد الأباء والذي يعاني
is suffering from a developmental disorder,
طفله من اظطراب في النمو،
then perhaps one more puzzle
إذن لربما سيتم معالجة لغز آخر
in one more brain will be solved.
داخل أحد الأدمغة.
One more mind will be unlocked.
دماغ اخر سيتم تحريره
And one more child who has been misdiagnosed
وطفل آخر تم تشخيص حالته خطأ
or even undiagnosed by the system
أو حتى لم يشخص عن طريق النظام
will finally realize his or her true potential
سيدرك أخيرًا امكانياته الحقيقة
while there's still time
حينما يتوفر الوقت
for his or her brain to recover.
لدماغه ليتعافى.
And all this by simply watching the child's brainwaves.
وكل هذا عن طريق مشاهدة موجات الدماغ للطفل.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)